<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good conscience. Or, The soules banquet royall. In a sermon by T.P.</title>
            <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849808</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09507)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 902:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good conscience. Or, The soules banquet royall. In a sermon by T.P.</title>
                  <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Thomas Creede, for Arthur Iohnson, and are to bee solde at his shoppe in Paules Churchyard, at the White Horse, neere the great north dore of S. Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Pestell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14977:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14977:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14977:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14977:2"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE AND worthy Knight, Sir <hi>Philip Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope</hi> of <hi>Shelford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing a good CONSCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCE to be euery honorable, &amp; (indeed) euery honeſt mans Saint and Miſtreſſe (in both which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, I aſſure my ſelfe you haue a large &amp; plentiful intereſt) I haue ventured here to preſent to ſuch mens viewes in generall, a poore and rough draught of her perfection; and in ſpeciall, to you as one, to whom it ſhall be no diſgrace, that I account you amongſt her principall ſeruants: which beleefe in your affection, and deuotion to her, draws me to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in your inclination to pardon, and withall to accept this (in truth vnskilfull) picture that here I ſend you, though it bee as far from the life, as earth is from heauen. I ſhall happily bee cenſured for not ſelecting othermore ſpecious ſeruants, &amp; fauourites of hers, which boaſt and make a face of great atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts and endeuours, and employments of their valour, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14977:3"/>integrity, in the full maintenance and preſeruation of her noble and God-like temper, and in aduancing of her deſerued honour and reputation: but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I haue euer found (in that weake diſcouery, which my feeble vnderſtanding could make of men) thoſe which excell in brauery, and number of wordes and profeſsion, to fall ſhort in deedes and execution, and on the contrary, leaſt proſerers, beſt performers.</p>
            <p>And therefore as notwithſtanding the want of glorious &amp; flouriſhing Proteſtations (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly faltring in performance) and maugre the ſpight and diueliſh deuiſes of your enemies (in whom it is a hard queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether their malice or follie be greater) ſeeking to auile and miniſh your hearts faithfulneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity: I yet do firmely credit the vnfained reſpect you beare to that heauenly Miſtreſſe of yours: ſo I deſpaire not of faire interpretation and acceptance at your hands of this her purtraiture: though (as I told you) done ſo ruggedly. The pouerty of which offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, I haue no means to relieue, but by praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God long to continue your health and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rtey; to bleſſe both your outward and inward eſtate: and that therein you may dayly indeed manifeſt your ſelfe, to be what I fully beleeue you are; namely, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer and a patrone to a good conſcience. So with the ſignification of that duty and ſeruice, which I am iuſtly tyed to tender both you and your worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady, I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your command, THOMAS PESTELL:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14977:3"/>
            <head>THE GOOD CONSCIENCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV: 15.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A good Conſcience is a continuall Feast.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Text is mention of two things, which (it ſeems) the world hath quite forgotten; at leaſt left off, and diſaccuſtomed. It may bee wee haue heard our Fathers, or Grand-fathers report ſtrange things, of Lordes, &amp; Knights, and great Men, keeping bountifull houſes and continuall Feaſts, and they perchaunce heard their Fathers before them ſpeake of keeping a good Conſcience. But in this <hi>Rotten, Woodden-Age,</hi> wherin we liue, theſe two are periſht, at leaſt traueld and gone out of the Land together, which together we find as faſt frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in the text, <hi>A good conſcience, &amp; a continuall Feast.</hi> All I hope to gaine is, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of ſuch things will not be vnwelcome to vs, becauſe wee are fallen vpon thoſe times, indeed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: wherein men are meerely nothing but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and talke of theſe matters.</p>
            <p>In opening the Text, foure ſeuerall things are to be enquired of, and ſtood vpon.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14977:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, what Conſcience is in generall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What a good Conſcience is, and the contrary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The main intendment of <hi>Solomon</hi> in this place, or the generall Doctrine hence obſerueable, hauing two branches, one implicite, which is, that wicked ſoules are moſt anguiſhed, and wheeled, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with affliction, moſt grieued &amp; galled in minde: another explicite, to wit, that good and honeſt men are more mirthfull, ioyous, receyue more true ſolace and contentment, then the former.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How this compariſon heere vrged by <hi>Salomon</hi> may be fitted and applied; prouing firſt that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked conſcience is no feaſt, or if one, not continuall. Secondly, in the righteous, that theyrs is one, and a continuall one. <hi>A good Conſc: is a &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt, what Conſcience is in generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is defined to bee a certaine naturall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Lawe, approuing honeſt and good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diſallowing or deteſting ſuch as bee ill: Or it is a iudgement of the ſoule, fetched from the Law of God, vppon which enſues eyther a ioyfulnes, or a trembling in the ſoule. And it conſiſts (ſaieth <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi>) of a practicke <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> in mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the hearts motion that enſues it. The <hi>Maior</hi> whereof is the rule of certaintie and truth, to which the deede is layde, and weighed in the <hi>Minor:</hi> and the concluſion is the ſoules Iudgement, or refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on it ſelfe, procuring eyther quietnes or vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> defines it to bee: <hi>Ordo ſcientiae ad aliquid,</hi> an Act by which wee applie our knowledge to ſome-particular thing. And <hi>Caluin</hi> ſayes, t'is <hi>Medium quid dam,</hi> a certaine thing of a middle nature twixt God and man, not ſuffering a man to ſuppreſſe in himſelfe what hee knowes offenſiue to God. <hi>Lypſius</hi> calls it <hi>Sointillam:</hi> A ſparckle of rectified reaſon, left ſtill in man, of his good and euill actions, both <hi>Iudex</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14977:4"/>
               <hi>Iudex,</hi> both Iudge and witneſſe. To which purpoſe it hath bene named, the Pulſe, the Spurre, the Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the watchman, the clock or <hi>Laerum</hi> to the ſoule; the good <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> foretelling dangers, Gods ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Bayliffe and Secretary, to arreſt vs, to regiſter our offences, of which that is true of <hi>Tullie, Magnum vim habet in vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partem, &amp;c.</hi> It hath great force on both ſides, eyther to free them from feare, who haue done nothing, or to preſent euer to theyr face due puniſhment that be offendors, whervnto agrees that deſcription of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the ſcriptures, that it is our owne Thoughts, eyther accuſing or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence wee may eaſily deſcend to the ſecond particular, and gaine the vnderſtanding of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which yet will be hard to doe: in regard a good oue is indeed the very <hi>Peace of GOD,</hi> which paſſeth all vnderſtanding; yet thus farre they haue cleared vs, who define it to bee a ioyfull reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of a well-led de life, ioyned with hope, in the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Comfortable euent: or a ioyous motion of the ſoule, ioyned <hi>cùm ſcientià,</hi> with knowledge of her own right actions, (in which regard it is named con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certly, <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not meerely <hi>Science,</hi> for without this coniunction it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience nicknamed, or miſcalled:) and wee are eaſed by ſuch, who holde a Conſcience then to bee free or good when it is at peace, eyther concerning pardon of ſinne, or concerning our pleaſing God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all imperfections: or when the queſtion is of things in theyr owne nature indifferent, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch a choyce, neither <hi>Aſinina,</hi> nor <hi>Lupina;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtraining at ſtrawes, nor ſwallowing logges. But then ſpecially, when it is calme and quiet vppon the firſt ground, namely, vppon the ſence of ſinne forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the ſoule made free &amp; reconciled to God, an eſtate, neither befalling the prowde <hi>Phariſee,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14977:5"/>ſwolne, and pufft vp with a falſe conception &amp; tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, a deceiuable confidence, and ouer-weening of his owne righteouſnes, nor the dull and ſtony ſinner, who drunk with ſinnes ſweetnes, is made inſenſible, and remains ſeemingly vndiſquieted. In ſumme, t'is nothing elſe but that inward integritie of the heart, whereof <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaking, ſayes, <hi>The ende and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Law, is Charitie in a pure heart, with faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. And preſently after, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. differencing it from a meer vnderſtanding, he ſaith, <hi>Some haue made a ſhipwracke of Faith, by forſaking a good Conſcience:</hi> Wherein (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi>) hee ſhewes it to be a liuely ardor of ſeruing God, with the entire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his ſoule; and a ſincere endeuour, to liue godly and honeſtly among men, reſpecting proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preciſely God, as the maine ende and obiect therof; but leſſe principally men, becauſe the effects and fruits of it extend euen to them alſo. This thus opened, brings vs (I hope) ſome light to finde and ſee what an euill Conſcience is, which is, whatſoeuer the former is not. A remembrance of an ill-led-life, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with feare of puniſhment, or a grieuous and rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king motion of the ſoule, mixt with knowledge and ſight of her owne wickednes, and by conſequence, with a foreſight of her owne miſerie. But in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the next part of the Text, we ſhall obtaine a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde diſcouerie of them both, and be made to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry aſwell the comfortable nature of the one, as the poore and wretched condition of the other.</p>
            <p>Come wee then to that which I called the maine intendment of <hi>Solomon,</hi> or the generall Doctrine hence obſerueable; The firſt part whereof is, that there is no peace to the wicked, as God ſpeakes by <hi>Eſay,</hi> No ioy, no comfort, in an ill ſoule. And the ſecond, That the good man, is the onely merrie man aliue. For ſo much is veiled and couered here, vnder theſe words. <hi>A continuall Feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14977:5"/>
            <p n="3">3 For the firſt, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of the good man that he is afflicted: yet alwayes merrie. So <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> of the wicked iuſt contrary, euen in laughter the heart is ſorrowfull, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.13. The world then (it ſeemes) is couſened and gulled with ſhowes and ſhadowes, and outward ſemblances, thinking ſuch a man ſicke that is in perfect health, eſteeming an other in great iollity, of an able luſty body, when t'is but a languiſhing carkaſſe. For the full worldling ſets out, and paints and ſtruts like a huge <hi>Coloſſus</hi> of gold (peraduenture) or Iuory without, but ſtuft with clay and ſtones within: all their happineſſe affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no more comfort, then for a theefe to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on a painted Gallowes. Therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> calls it <hi>Foelicitatem bracteatam, &amp; capſulam totam:</hi> gilded felicity, all couer and ſhell, and barke, ſtraw with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out graine, or gilded ſheathes with leaden wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: nor yet ſo merely? T'is not a froath or winde, or emptineſſe, but a burning, a corroſion, a ſting, a poyſon, a ſecret malignity withall: For ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> implyes, where ſpeaking of all outward things, hee ſayeth, They are not onely vanity, but vexation of the ſpirite. So that worldlings may complaine of all earthly matters, as <hi>Agarnemnon</hi> doth of honour in the Tragedy: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. T's ſweet (in ſhow and ſemblance a farre off) but it ſads a man at heart when it comes. The maine reaſon whereof is, that of <hi>Senecaes,</hi> becauſe all folly and vanity <hi>laborat faſtidió ſui,</hi> growes in the end weary of it ſelfe. <hi>Et maximam ſui veneni partem bibit,</hi> drinkes vp the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of her owne poyſon, occaſioned by a gnawn wormeaten, a wicked guilty conſcience. For as the <hi>Cruciaeries</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> bore that Croſſe which ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards beare them: ſo God hath layde this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as a croſſe on euery ſinnefull wretch, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee ſuffers before before time of his full and final ſuffering.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14977:6"/>
            <p>A thing which the Heathens felt and diſcouered, <hi>Sua quemque fraus &amp; ſuus terror maximè vexat</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Tullie</hi>) Each mans owne fraud, and his owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightment moſt diſquiets him, and thoſe <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> (ſayeth hee) doe anguiſh and purſue wicked men, not with burning firebrands, as wee ſee in Tragedies, <hi>ſed angore conſcientiae,</hi> but with the trouble of their conſcience. And <hi>Seneca</hi> moſt diuinely, <hi>Nihil prod ſt incluſam habere conſcientiam, patemus Deo. Quid quaeris? quid machinaris? quid abſcondis? custos tuus te ſequitur? Quid locum abdictum legis? arbitros remoues? Putas tibi contigiſſe, vt oculos ouium effugias?</hi> To what end (ſayeth he) Doth a ſinner chuſe ſecreſie, or ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſſe? <hi>Demens quid prodeſt non habere conſcium, cum habes conſcientiam?</hi> Madman, what auayles to haue no witneſſe of thy wickedneſſe, thou hauing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is a thouſand witneſſes.</p>
            <p>A thing which euery ſinner would ſhunne and cannot, whoſe ſtate is therefore reſembled to the ſtricken Beare, which running <hi>per ſyluas, ſaltuſque,</hi> through woods and groues, yet ſtill <hi>haeret lateri laetha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis arundo,</hi> the deadly arrow ſticks ſtill in her ſide; ſo runnes and rowles the perplexed ſinner like <hi>Lucans</hi> Beare, <hi>Se rotat in vulnus, &amp; ſecum fugientem circuit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam,</hi> though hee wheele and turne round (as the Wiſeman ſayth <hi>Impij ambulant in circuitu:</hi>) yet the Speare that wounded him fals not out. Such men, ſayeth <hi>Plutarch</hi> are like men ſea-ſicke, who being in the ſhippe, thinke they ſhould doe better in the boate, and thence backe againe to the ſhippe: <hi>nihil agunt, &amp;c.</hi> They doe nothing (ſayeth he) nothing to any purpoſe, ſo long as their choler remaines in the ſtomacke: So the Sinner, no ſhift of place, no change of ayre relieues him, being dogged and tended on by <hi>Erynnis Conſcientiae,</hi> the Helliſh Hagge, or fury of his conſcience, that euer-gaping <hi>Cerberus,</hi> that euer-waking blood hound; eyther barking eager, and ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14977:6"/>diſturbs his reſt, which is bad enough: or if it chance to ſleepe, it is farre worſe: if it wakes, it makes him like a mad-man; when it ſleepes; a Lethargique dull and ſenſeleſſe: if it ſpeake, a thouſand wild <hi>Chymae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raes</hi> and winged furies, and ſpirting ſerpents ride vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tongue of it: but when it is dumbe, it caſts him into a ſtony deadnes, which is an eſtate ſo dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as we are wont to expreſſe it by reſemblance to a Patient, on whom Phyſicke works not, or that ſeeles not himſelfe ſicke, when both Phyſitians and friends know him deſperate. Ti's-<hi>Auſtines, Quid mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerius miſero non miſerante ſeipſum?</hi> What more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable then a wretch, not to take compaſſion on himſelfe? Nor can it bee thought a pleaſure for a ſinner, that his ſoule is growne ouer with a filme or cataract, that he becomes obdurate, ſeared and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſeleſſe, and ſo ſecure like <hi>Ionas</hi> vnder hatches, a ſleepe: for ſuch a ſleepe of the conſcience is but a dogges ſleepe, as God tolde <hi>Cain, in Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>If thou doeſt ill, Sinne lyes at the dore, lyes like a dogge at the dore, vpon a ſodaine to riſe and plucke out his throat. Tandemiſta tranquilitas tempeſtas eſt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome</hi>) This ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming calme proues in the end a moſt cruell ſtorme: as a wheele ſeemes not at all to moue when it is whirled about with greateſt violence.</p>
            <p>Which if we would haue proued or exemplified (beſide prophane ſtories and dayly tryall) the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is plenteous in furniſhing vs with examples and teſtimonies: <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.15. It may be hee will hate vs, and pay vs againe the euill wee did him. A fuller example, is <hi>Herod</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. who when Chriſt came to offer mercy; out of the hell of his hart imagined <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> had bin riſen again to take vengeance. So the Scribes and Phariſees in that iudgement of our Sauiour, concerning the woman taken in adultery, accuſed of their owne conſcience, went out one by one, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.9. The ſame ſting it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14977:7"/>was made <hi>Baltazers</hi> countenance change, and his ioyntes to bee looſed, and his knees to knocke one againſt onother, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.6. So when <hi>Paul</hi> diſputed of righteouſneſſe and temperance, and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come: the Text ſayeth, <hi>Foelix</hi> trembled, Act. 24.26. The time would fayle mee to ſpeake of <hi>Adam,</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and ſixe hundred more: for it is in all wicked ſoules, eyther the firſt part of hell, a fire that burnes and conſumes ſpeedily; or the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, a worme that cloſely frets and eates away, and rots the ſoule, and ſhall neuer die, ſaith <hi>Eſay,</hi> 66 24. Such a man is like him the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.11. Who is damned of himſelfe, his owne Iudge, witnes, hangman: at leaſt findes himſelfe guiltie, and nothing remaines, but a fearefull looking for of iudgement, and a violent fire, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond branch of the doctrine, and that which is here expreſt, is, that how euer the worlde raſhly conceit good mens eſtate wretched and tempeſtuous, yet they are the onely merry men aliue. It is thought religion duls their wits, &amp; daunts their ſpirits, as if mirth and miſchiefe euer met together. But the Heathens haue beene able to tell vs, that all bliſſe lyes not in a giddy lightnes. There is (ſayeth <hi>Statius</hi>) <hi>hilaris cum pondere virtus,</hi> Vertue with mirth, and weight in it: and <hi>Tully</hi> could ſay: <hi>Non hilarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te modo, nec laſcinia, nec ioco comite lenitatis, ſed ſaepe etiam triſtes firmitate &amp; conſtantiâ ſunt beati:</hi> Men many times ſeeming ſad, are bleſſed in the firmeneſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of their temper. For the true Chriſtian man, though hee runne ſtill away: yet his ioyes are dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, then the ruſhing noyſe of ſhallow worldlings; as <hi>Claudius</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Nilus: Lene fluit, ſed cunctis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus exit vtilior, nullas confeſſus murmure vireis:</hi> though it ſhew no ſtrength in his murmure and ratling, yet it is more vſefull then other riuers. This is true of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14977:7"/>good conſcience, in the generall, becauſe it is in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſeaſe a Phyſition, in ſtrife a Lawyer, in doubt a Preacher, in grieſe a counſellor, in ſinne a confeſſor; like a ſweet perſume, at once taking away the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſmell, and leauing a ſweet ſauour for it, or like the Vnicorns horne in water, driuing poyſon out of any eſtate. This we ſhall in like maner find true, if we take into our conſideration thoſe things which moſt afflict and trauell men in this life, and wherewith the beſt men are oftentimes ſhaken and diſturbed, and theit evennes interrupted and en combred, which be SIN and Affliction. For we ſhall finde that which <hi>Iuvenal</hi> ſpeakes of vertue; <hi>Semita tranquillae per vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem patet vnica vitae,</hi> applyable more fitly to a good conſcience, that the way out of the forenamed diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and the path to arriue at quietnes is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And for SIN firſt, the dayly wraſtlings &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates againſt thoſe reliques of ſin, are beſt known to them that haue experienced them: Such will cry out in the bitternes of their ſoules, with S. <hi>Paul, I feele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother law in my members, rebelling againſt the law of my fleſh, and leading mee captiue into the law of ſinne. O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death?</hi> Rom. 7.23.24. Now a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth not onely preſerue men from committing ſome ſinne, as Pride and enuy (that Saw of the ſoule, and paine of the damned, and ſo works a peacefull innocency that way: but it likewiſe cleares him from the guilt and horror of all ſinne: For firſt, it is a procurer, at leaſt, a faſt friend, to a bolde &amp; liuelie faith in God. So the Author to the Hebrewes, Heb. 10.22. Let vs draw neare in aſſurance of our faith with a true heart, ſprinckled in our hearts from an euill conſcience; and then in the next place it makes a man confident to come with boldnes to the throne of grace: for if our heart condemn vs not, then haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14977:8"/>we confidence towards God, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.21. In which regard <hi>Dauid</hi> ftiles God the God of his prayſe, &amp; the God of his righteouſnes: and the Apoſtle cals inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of life, and a good conſcience, <hi>arma inſtitiae,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of righteouſneſſe on the right hand, and on the left, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. which preſerues him ſafe from all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and ſnares, and temptations of the diuell: nay, the righteous man gaines by euery ſuch attempt of Sathan: <hi>Doemones tentando nobis coronas fabricant,</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry temptation anoyded, as it is a Crown to a man; ſo it is a curſe to his enemy. And <hi>Origen</hi> imagined, that it ſhould increaſe the tormentors puniſhment. In the meane time, the righteous ſoule lyes couered vnder his buckler of Faith, like little <hi>Teucer</hi> vnder the ſhield of <hi>Aiax,</hi> ſecure from danger. Nay, Sin indeed hath now no further power to endamage him: for as the ſpirite of God becomming his boſome friend, doth like a new <hi>Hercules</hi> kill that rauening vulture, which tyres vpon the liuer of his poore ſoule, and when hee is in greateſt anguiſh, that he prayes and ſighes, and grones, then that prayes for him, ſighes, grones for him with ſuch ſighes, ſuch groanes ſo oppreſſed, as they cannot bee expreſſed: Rom. 8.26. So Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus his ſauiour and mighty Redeemer, hath pulled out the ſting of it, the poyſon and virulency, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity is taken away by him. For the ſtrength of ſin is the Law; now ſuch men, ſayth the Apoſtle, are no longer vnder the Law, but vnder grace. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is bold to ſay of ſuch a man: Hee do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſinne, nor can doe none: a ſtrange ſpeech; yet moſt true; hee cannot ſinne fearefully, finally, with the whole ſway and bent of his minde and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or doeth no ſinne which ſhall bee imputed to him, or layde to his charge, as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.33.34. where hee ſeemes to giue out a generall callenge againſt all commers: to doe their worſt, to vrge the vtmoſt they can. T'is &amp;c. (ſaith he)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14977:8"/>Who is that man ſo hardy as dare tax the children of God? Who ſhal lay anything to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that iuſtifies, who ſhall condemne? &amp;c. So that in ſuch men, ſinne though it remaine, yet it doth not raigne there, but is onely like a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing carcaſe in the graue, daily rotting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming away: they ſhall ſinne ſo long as they beare about fleſh and blood, wherein dwells corruption: they that fall, cannot but be ſubiect to many weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: yet if they haue a good Conſcience, their fall is not like the fall of the <hi>Elephant,</hi> which being down, cannot riſe againe; but contrarie, their falls teach them better how to ſtand, and their infirmitie ſerues to confirme the vertue of their Conſtancie: And (which is the ſoueraine ioy of Gods people) in euery ſinfull tentation, they doe like <hi>Hercules, exire maiores,</hi> growe greater, which <hi>S. Paul</hi> meanes, where he ſayes <hi>Become more then Conquerours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And as thus they are not depreſſed by this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, ſo neither doe they ſtoope or ſtand in ſeare of the other, which is affliction. It is a bitter thing to looke into the manifolde diſtreſſes and incombian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to be met and encountred; yet a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences abides the iniurie and aſſault &amp; batterie of them all, vnmoued and vnappalled, — <hi>Illiſos fluctus rupes, vt vaſta refundit,</hi> Like a rock, againſt which a thouſand Billows riſe and roare, yet the ſtone for all their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and foaming keepes his place, and beates them in pieces. So the ſoule of ſuch a man is like <hi>Socrates,</hi> who was euer in one countenance: nay, it is in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, like fire in winde, more enflamed: as a Traueller meeting in hindrance, wilbe more eager on his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: like golde in the furnace, neither leſſened in his weight, through differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or diſtruſt of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Though he kill mee, yet ſtill I will truſt in him:</hi> nor evaporates, or goes away in fume &amp; impatient follie. In all theſe things did not <hi>Iob</hi> ſinne with his mouth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14977:9"/>nor charge God fooliſhly, but ſhines out freſher and purer then before, in an holie life and conuerſation. And after hee hath ſtood the ſhocke, and paſſed the ſtorme of many afflictions, he can yet encourage and cheere his ſorrowful Fortunes, ſpeaking of his good conſcience, as <hi>Hecuba</hi> of <hi>Polixena,</hi> when the reſt were dead. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Good men indeed ſeeme the pooreſt and moſt wretched things on earth; and are counted as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the very off-ſcowring of all things. <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> and hee, had pretie ſhares in affliction: And a man that ſhould read <hi>Iobs</hi> book, and <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalms, and <hi>S Paules</hi> Epiſtles, would maruell to heare that theſe men were ſo merrie. There is plenteous men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faſting, of teares, of bonds, of cold impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nakednes, &amp;c: But wher's this ioy, this conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feaſt we talke of? Let the man that moues ſuch queſtions, knowe for certaine, that hee vnderſtands not ſuch mens eſtates aright: For the true Chriſtian man is a bundle and world of wonders, running con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary courſes, like the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> ſtrong when they are weake, as the Moon waining to the earthward, wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth towards heauen: Therefore (<hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>I take pleaſure in infirmities, in reproches, in neceſſities, in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in anguiſh, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. Indeed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the wicked is like a compound Medicine: There muſt be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ing, and dancing, and dallying, or they cannot ſeeme merrie, but the godly mans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is of another ſtraine, a newe kinde, like a light ſhining in the ayre, when no matter is ſeene to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it. We are miſtaken then, if we thinke ſuch men vpon earth, it is true, we ſee them heare, as we ſee the Moone and ſtarres in water, but they are in heauen: S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith plainely, our conuerſation is in Heauen already: Their ſoule is where it would be; as <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> of <hi>Mary Magdalene: Maria ubi nos erat, vbi erat, &amp;c.</hi> She was not where ſhe was for ſhe was wholly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14977:9"/>where her Maſter was. Hence is it, that when the worldlings ſhrinks, and ſinkes vnder a little trouble, they beare it out brauely, and with a kind of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcorne trample on all encombrances: So <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes diſdainefully of tribulation: Who ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from the loue of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, &amp;c. as though hee thought it vnworthy the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon of this is nothing but the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of theſe mens ſoules and conſciences, aſſuring them firſt, that all afflictions are momentany for a night, ioy returning in the morning: or if they laſt longer, yet the Prophet <hi>Oſee</hi> tels vs:After two daies hee will reuiue vs, and the third day hee will raiſe vs vp. <hi>Oſe.</hi> 6.2. Secondly, theyr conſcience tels them how iuſtly theſe things are inflicted; that the ſtore of corruption in them deſerues not onely this fire of affliction to purge them, but euen hell fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them: that as God alway rewards <hi>ſupra meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> aboue mans deſert: ſo he puniſheth <hi>citra iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> on this ſide his iuſtice: and then thirdly makes them know that they are needfull (for wiping away all teares in heauen, doth neceſſarily pteſuppoſe wet eyes on earth, reſting their toyle and labour here) and alſo good for them: <hi>Dona Dei admonentis,</hi> the good gift of God admoniſhing vs, ſayeth <hi>Auſtin:</hi> It is good for mee (ſayeth <hi>Dauid</hi>) Nay they are not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, medidicines of their health and ſafety; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpecial toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Gods fatherly loue and kindneſſe, as the Apoſtle reaſons, Heb. 12.8. If yee bee without correction, then are yee baſtards and not ſonnes.</p>
            <p>So that men being once armed with this armour and ſtrength of a ſound heart and good conſcience, like <hi>Dauid</hi> with his ſtone and ſling, no vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Philiſtine</hi> can diſmay him, nothing in the world can ſound to his diſcomfort. <hi>Vbi in altum delati ſumus,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14977:10"/>when wee are carried into the deepe of calamity and trouble, it is then the anker of a good conſcience, (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi>) that keepes vs fuſe, that preſerues our ſoules from periſhing in the waters. If afflictions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe like a ſpring of bitter waters: yet the ſalt of a good conſcience will ſeaſon this ſpring, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall bee healed: or is thy griefe yet greater, &amp; riſen to a flood, euen as the flood of <hi>Iordane,</hi> that thou mayeſt cry with the Pſalmiſt; The waters are come in (Lord) euen to my very ſoule; yet faint not, for the vertue of a good conſcience, like the ſpirite of God in <hi>Elias</hi> will cut this <hi>Iordane,</hi> and thou ſhalt goe ouer it in ſafety; or yet more, if the courſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of thy afflictions be ſwolne and riſen to a ſea; whoſe waues are madde, and rage horribly; yet thy good conſcience, ſhall like the Arke of <hi>Noah</hi> beare thee aboue the pride and power of all thoſe ſurges, ouer whoſe backes thou ſhalt ride like another <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in mirth and triumph: or laſt of all, if it come to the worſt of all terrible afflictions, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to a red and bloody ſea of tribulation and perſecution: why? yet feare not, ſtand ſtill, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſaluation of the Lord: the ſpirite of God in the teſtimony of thy good conſcience, will ſpeake peace to thy affrighted ſoule; nay, like <hi>Moyſes</hi> will ſtretch his hand and his rod ouer this ſea, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide it, and thou ſhalt paſſe on drie ground through the midſt thereof.</p>
            <p>And as thus afflictions in generall do not endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the true and righteous ſeruants of God, but that they are bulwarkes and defenced againſt them; ſo wee ſhall finde it true by running ouer ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>Let there bee warre and deuaſtation, ſacking &amp; burning of townes, rauiſhing of Matrones and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, and all the retinue of rage and horror enter vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a land with noyſe of weapons, and tumbling of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14977:10"/>garments in blood, as the Prophet deſcribes it: yet all this will not breake his truce with heauen; he ſhal in the midſt of warre enioy that peace which Chriſt left his Diſciples, That peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding. Let it bee rumorde that all the braue and daring men in the world are comming on: nay, let him bee aſſured, (as vndoubtedly hee is from the word of God) that all the Peeres and Princes of Hell are vp in Armes; Principalities and powers, and worldly gouernours, Princes of the darkneſſe of this world ſpirituall wickedneſſe in hie places, are banded and leagued againſt him: yet he will bee able, not onely to reſiſt in the euill day, but hauing finiſhed all things to ſtand faſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12.13. And where the Apoſtle there mentions a girdle of verity, and ſhooes of preparation, a breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, and a ſhield of faith, an helmet of ſaluation, and a ſword of the ſpirite, wee muſt know that hee which hath a good conſcience, hath all this furniture, this complete harneſſe of a Chriſtian alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. For that alone is the armour of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the right hand, and on the left, which makes a good man, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks bold as a Lion, valiant as <hi>Gedeon,</hi> or <hi>Sampſon,</hi> afrayde neyther of the arrow (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) that flies by night, nor the plague which deſtroyes at noon day. Nothing, nothing can diſmay the reſolute Chriſtian, <hi>Stelliger mundus ſonet, flammas &amp; hic &amp; ille iaculetur polus:</hi> Let the earth bee moued (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) and the foundation of it ſhake, &amp; the mountains be caſt into the midſt of the ſea, I will not feare, <hi>Si fractus illabatur orbis, impauidum fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient ruinae,</hi> though the world cracke and flie off the hindges, yet this ſhal nor apall him, but his heart wil be ſtill like the hart of the <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> firme as a ſtone, and as hard as a peece of the neyther milſtone, <hi>Iob.</hi> 41.15.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch a man bee defamed, cauſeleſly tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14977:11"/>in his good Name: yet <hi>Tullie</hi> was able to ſay <hi>Conſcientia virtuti ſatis amplum Theatrum:</hi> A good Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is a Theater large enough for vertue: and the man that is not guiltie, or conſcious to himſelfe, of deſeruing infamy, hath (ſaith <hi>Horace</hi>) <hi>Murum ahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum,</hi> a wall of braſſe, to retort and ſhoot into theyr owne boſomes, all theſe fiery dartes of the wicked.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes indeed that this ſcourge of Tongues, is no meane vexation, for <hi>Dauid</hi> calles ſuch detraction by the names of Swordes, and ſpeares, and ſharpe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and poyſoned dartes: and complaines miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in his Pſalmes, an 100. times at leaſt, how cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly hee was galled and infeſted with ſuch weapons: yet both hee and all the children of God from time to time haue vſed no other rampire, but this of a good conſcience, which they haue euer ſound ſo firme and ſolide, that it hath been able in middeſt of the hotteſt aſſaults, not to preſerue from danger on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to powre into them, a noble contempt of their aſſailers, and a ſpirituall complacency, in this kinde of calamity, as wee heard from Saint <hi>Paules</hi> teſtimony of himſelfe, I take pleaſure in infirmities (and next addes) in reproches, in perſecutions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let it be pouerty; to him it is an eſtate full of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe hath made it glorious; and the Heathen hath tolde him, <hi>Facile conſolatur honestas egeſtatem:</hi> Pouerty is ſoone cheared vp with honeſty: if hunger or thirſt aſſayle him, hee hath a good conſcience to feed him, which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Feaſt, aſſuring him the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſtands not in meate and drinke. Nay, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man is ſo far from affrightment at ſuch trifles, that <hi>Elihu</hi> tels vs, When famine comes, then comes his ioy, his delight: a deſtruction and famine, hee ſhall laugh, and though death be to wicked men <hi>vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum terribilium,</hi> a dampe, a dampe that puts out all their light, and marres their muſicke: yet to an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14977:11"/>honeſt heart, and a good conſcience, it brings rather an affluence of comfort and reioycing, a thing, the children of God wiſh and long for; <hi>Cupio diſſolui,</hi> I deſire to bee diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt Ieſus. So that in all afflictions, how great, how grieuous ſoeuer the conſcience of a godly man is not diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; it may perchance ſlacken it ſelfe, and bee ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered or diſſolued at the firſt encounter: but when it returnes into it ſelfe, and arreſts on the holy ſpirite of God, and ſtrength of his grace, it doth not onely ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from all ſuch wauerings and weakeneſſes; but it growes ſo firme and bolde, as to take ioy and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace therein, when that which before was ſowre and diſtaſtfull, becomes ſweet and gracious.</p>
            <p>And this muſt needes be ſo, it needs no proofe; for how can it bee otherwiſe; but that Gods children ſhould bee men of ioy; glad men, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.3. Leaping for ioy; when wee are taught by God himſelfe, that his Kingdome is the place of ioy; nay, nothing elſe but peace &amp; ioy in the holy Ghoſt; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. and his Goſpell the matter of ioy, as the Angell proclaimes from heauen: Behold I bring you tidings of great ioy, that ſhall be to all people. To this purpoſe we haue plentifull teſtimonies in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that God will euer keepe and defend his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſeruants tenderly, as the apple of his eye: beares them ſafe from danger, as he did the Iſraelites vpon his wings: as vpon a featherbed, ſoft and ſecure; he giues his Angels charge ouer them, that they daſh not their foot againſt a ſtone; or if any one chance to fall, <hi>Siceciderit,</hi> ſayth <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet hee ſhall not periſh; for the Lord puts vnder his hand. The Lions doe lacke, and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeeke the Lord ſhall want no manner of thing that is good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10. Many ſorrowes to the wicked, but he that truſts in the Lord, mercy imbraceth him on euery ſide. Be glad, ô yce righteous, ſhowt for ioy, all yee that are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14977:12"/>true of heart. Pſal. 32.10.11. The voyce of ioy and reioycing, and ſaluation, ſhall bee in the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the righteous. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.15. (ſayeth <hi>Solomon</hi>) anſweres a good man in the ioy of his heart, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. <hi>vlt.</hi> They that obey and ſerue him ſhall ſpend &amp; end their dayes in proſperity, and their dayes in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and their yeares in pleaſure, <hi>Iob.</hi> 36.11. God giues ſuch (ſayeth <hi>Eſaie</hi>) beauty for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for mourning, the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirite of heauines. And as wee haue it in promiſe from God; ſo in example of godly men that haue euer found it ſo, as <hi>Dauid,</hi> who out of his experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne many Pſalmes with prayer, and ends them with thankſgiuing. And the bleſſed Virgine, My Soule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirite hath reioyced in God my Sauiour. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum exemplorum:</hi> all his ſpeech of himſelfe is but a comment on this Text, and a large expoſition of this point in hand. Hee confeſſeth it. Our reioyſing is this, the teſtimony of our conſcience, and in the 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4. I ouerflow exceedingly, I abound with all ioy amidſt our tribulations; and that it is the generall condition of all Gods ſeruants: Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tels vs, where he ſayeth, that though they ſee him not, yet beleeuing, reioyce with ioy vnſpeakeable, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
            <p>This might eaſily be proued, by ſhewing that ſuch men haue all the true grounds &amp; foundations of ioy and contentment; As firſt, that they haue remiſſion of ſinnes in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and ſecondly, adoption to become the Sonnes of God: and in the thirde place, haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight and title to Heauen: but tis <hi>Horaces</hi> counſell, <hi>quaedam dicenda remittere,</hi> not to amaſſe and heape vp all that might be ſaid to any one point; and therfore we come to the laſt part; namely, the fitting and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of this reſemblance, heere vrged by <hi>Solomon,</hi> wherin following the former Method, I will firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14977:12"/>to your conſideration howe the wicked conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is no Feaſt, or if one, not a continuall one: and next, that the good Conſcience is one, and ſecondly, a continuall one. <hi>A good Conſcience is a continuall Feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, wicked men haue no feaſt: For ſuch men haue loſt all taſt of good and heauenly things: They doe not reliſh or ſauour the things that bee of God, ſaith the Apoſtle, as we ſee Swine neglect paſture and eat draffe; So theſe men banquet, but t'is with poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, like <hi>Tereus</hi> feaſt, or rather t'is <hi>Scilicornium,</hi> a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Feaſt, for ſuch a man (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaks of a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow) that liues in the pleaſure of ſinne, is dead while he liues. Their food breeds onely winde, and froath, and inflation, no perfect, or pure blood: So that wee miſtake iudging ſuch a man full, becauſe Rich, tis true, he hath enough, his bellyful, but t'is with wind, <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 5.16. or elſe theyr eating procures a corroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and convulſion, priuie gripings, and qualmes, ſtitches and aches, wormes, and diſtortion of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtomacke, that they cannot ſleepe or take reſt vpon it. The ſatietie of the Rich will not ſuffer him to ſleepe. Or if hee doe, hee ſhall ſpue ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) hee hath deuoured ſubſtance, and ſhall vomite it: for God ſhall draw it out of his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>Iob.</hi> 20. Or if it ſettle and ſtay with him, then it inflames his ſoule, and hart-burnes him: For a prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed ſinner is ſaide to haue his ſoule ſinged and ſeared, his Conſcience burnt with an hotte yron. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. or laſtly, as poyſon, if it kill not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, breakes out in tumors and byles: ſo his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doth occaſion diſeaſes, and his bones are full of the ſinne of his Youth. <hi>Iob,</hi> 20.11. and as he goeth on, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. Though wickednes be ſweet in his mouth, and though he hide it vnder his tongue, and keepe it (like a delicate <hi>Epicure</hi>) in the midſt of his palate; yet his meat in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of <hi>Aſpes</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14977:13"/>within him. And this is theyr viandes, their cates, theyr delicates: of which <hi>Dauid</hi> deſires to eate no part, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 141. If wee deſire to knowe what they drinke at ſuch a feaſt, <hi>Iob</hi> tells vs they drinke iniquity like water: <hi>Iob:</hi> 15.16. and their wine the ſcripture ſaith, is the wine of aſtoniſhment; or elſe a certaine kind of compounded ſtuffe, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaks of: <hi>pſ:</hi> 75.8. <hi>In the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Lord, ther is a cup, &amp; it is red wine: it is full mixt, and hee powres out of the ſame:</hi> Surely all the wicked of the earth ſhal wring out, &amp; drink ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 11. he deſcribes their burnt wine, which ſeemes the very ſame that the Deuils drinke in hell. God will raine ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tempeſt: this ſhalbe the portion of their cuppe. As for the companie of theſe men, what can it be, but a noyſe and ſette of Diuells: for Satan returning (ſaith our Sauiour) returning, and finding ſuch mens hearts, like houſes ſwept and garniſhed, prepared for him, enters with ſeuen worſe then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the ende of that man is worſe then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. It is not ſtrange then, that prophane and lewde men will fancie and conceite themſelues the onely flouriſhing people vpon earth: when wee ſee that their very banquetting ſtuffe is but gall &amp; poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, theyr drinke vengeance, and their companie Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells. But let vs grant them that their ſeeming mirth and iollity they liue in, may be tearmed a feaſt (which is their portion vpon earth; &amp; all they can looke for,) yet alaſſe, it is not a continuall feaſt, but exceeding fleet and momentanie. Euen in laughter, the heart is ſorrowfull; at that very inſtant. They banquet as theeues in a caue or a wood, alwayes in feare. <hi>Eſay</hi> tels vs that the Harpe, the Violl, the Tabret &amp; Pipe are in their feaſts, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 5.12. But this will not hold: for hee addes in ver. 14 Therefore Hell hath enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her ſelfe, and opened her mouth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de. And their pompe, and he that reioyceth ſhall deſcend into it:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14977:13"/>So ſoone they are gone. They breake off, as it were in the middeſt of their meale, and ſinke into hel. Nor can the damned ſoule thinke to take it out, when hee comes there. Indeed as hee in his life time made a feaſt of his ſoule to the Diuell, and dreſt it for him to make his Helſhip merry: (for as the good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels reioyce at a ſinners conuerſion: ſo wee muſt thinke the Diuels mirth is his rebellion.) So now Sathan to bee quiet with him, prepares him a feaſt, a blacke banquet, onely two diſhes, weeping ſerued in for the firſt courſe, and gnaſhing of teeth, for the ſecond: It is true, it ſhall bee a continuall feaſt: but worſe to him then any feaſt: for he ſhall bee ſo farre from receyuing pleaſure in it, that hee ſhall howle &amp; roare out with <hi>Diues,</hi> for ſome drinke to his hote meate, euen for a drop of water to coole his tongue: And this for the firſt part of the compariſon.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, that the goodman hath in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience a feaſt, and not ſo onely, but a continuall Feaſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, hee hath a Feaſt: for a godly man (like that vngodly one in the Goſpell) fares deliciouſly euery day; keepes a ſpirituall Chriſtmas alwayes, drinkes deepe in the Wine-ſellar, as it ſeemes by the Spouſe in Canticles, 2.4.5. <hi>Hee brought mee into the Wine-ſeller, and loue was his banner ouer mee. Stay mee with flaggons, and comfort me with apples, for I am ſicke of loue.</hi> So it is in that ſong of the bleſſed Virgin; Hee filles the hungry with good things: fils them, giues them enough, feaſts them: Like a noble Lord God, with his proper gifts and graces. And in examining, wee ſhall find that they haue all things, which make vp a ſumptuous Feaſt, and a BANQVET Royall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Plenty and variety of meat and drinke, 2. Good company. 3. Lights, and 4. Muſicke.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They haue plenty and change of diſhes; and they are all good ſolide meates. One maine ſeruice
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14977:14"/>is their ſeruice of God, their good worke: for it is a ioy to the iuſt to do iuſtice, <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.15. <hi>Dauid</hi> found it ſo. Pſal. 122.1. and in Pſalme 84. <hi>My ſoule longs, yea, and faints for the Courts of the Lord;</hi> And our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour confeſſeth it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. <hi>My meate is to doe the will of him that ſent me, and finiſh his worke:</hi> yet this to the moſt holy man aliue, is but a faint food in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſecond meſſe or ſeruice, whereupon they feed, and that is their faith in God: which is nouriſhing meat indeed: ſo ſayth the Scripture, The iuſt man ſhall liue by his faith: It is his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> his meat, his maintenance, and this feeds him thicke-fat: Hee that puts his ſure truſt in the Lord ſhall bee fat, <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.25. To which meat, his bread and drinke are hearty ſorrow and repentance for his ſin: So ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> God giues his people bread of teares, and teares to drinke in great meaſure whole healthes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.5. In the third place, the righteous ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates and feeds vpon God himſelfe, all the three perſons in the thrice bleſſed Trinity: Firſt, ſhe feaſts vpon God her Creator, taſts and ſees how gracious the Lord is, that not onely prouided a world to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine her, &amp; vnder a ſtarry cloth of State, did place a thouſand creatures, and diſtil a thouſand dewes for the refection of her body; but alſo feedes and fattes her ſelfe with his grace and goodnes: and this diſh, (if we will beleeue Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) is a wondrous ſweet one: <hi>Reuerâ, illudſolum eſt gaudium quod de crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore concipitur; cui comparata omnis aliunde iucunditas moeror eſt, omnis ſuanitas dolor est, omne dulce amarum eſt:</hi> Indeed that is is onely true delight which wee conceiue of our Creator: in regard whereof all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſure is a very bitterneſſe. And this made <hi>Auſtine</hi> cry out; <hi>O luxurioſe, vbi maior delectatio quam inſùmmi dulciſſime deo?</hi> Where canſt thou find more ſweetnes, then in the moſt ſweet God himſelfe? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the ſoule takes a ſweet repaſt on the ſecond
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14977:14"/>Perſon Chriſt Jeſus, from whoſe fulnes we doe all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue grace. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.16. Whoſe fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood is drinke indeed: of which whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eates and drinkes (ſaieth our Sauiour, hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life: <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.54. Who teſtifies alſo, that he is the true bread which came downe from heauen to ſtrengthen mans heart, and wine to comfort it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no adulterate or ſophiſtocate mixture, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the true vine. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15. to temper which heauenlie liquor, the ſoule in the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d place mixes it, with the water of the holy ſpirit, which is not meerely water; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Sweet and liuing water, ſpringing vp into euerlaſting life. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p>A fourth ſeruice, is a maine ſtanding diſh, and a delicate one, named the <hi>Mercy</hi> of God; therefore called by <hi>Dauid,</hi> not only plenteous mercy, but ſweet and tender mercy, which is not meerely foode, but a kind of reſtoratiue, as we may ſee in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 79.8. where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes, as if hee were in a conſumption; make haſte, and preuent vs with thy tender mercies: For wee are brought very low. And in the fift courſe comes in the <hi>Grace</hi> of God, whereof (as in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy they ſay, we are nouriſhed by the ſame things, of which wee are begotten,) we are both borne and maintained, both bred and fed: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth plainely: By the grace of God I am that I am, both in root and height: and this alſo is a ſtanding diſh, and taſtes like the barrel of meale, and cruiſe of oyle 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.16 or like that lake &amp; pot of water, which the Angell gaue <hi>Elias,</hi> after which hee aroſe, and did walke in the ſtrength of that meat forty dayes, and forty nights, 1. Reg. 19.8. It is indeed a whole Feaſt of it ſelfe. So God tolde Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Cor. 12.9. My grace is ſufficient for thee: ſufficient enough, and enough (wee ſay) is as good as a Feaſt. Next to make vp our meale are ſerued in the word of God, and the Sacrament of Chriſts moſt bleſſed body and blood,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14977:15"/>on which the firſt the ſoule doth feede and feaſt: for it is a ſtrong meate to faſten and confirme the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoule in faith, a medicine of immortality: An Antidote (ſaith <hi>Ignatius</hi>) aſſuring vs, wee ſhal not die but liue in Ieſus Chriſt: So for the word of God, it is called bread, Deut. 8. <hi>Amos</hi> threatens a famine of it, <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. And in Hebrewes 5. It is ſayde to bee milke for Babes, and ſtrong meate for men of riper age: and therefore God bade the Prophet eate the roule: and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayeth, hee tooke the Booke out of the Angels hand, and eate it vp: and to proue it more then ordinary food, S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals it wholeſom doctrine, and comfortable, that we through patience &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of the ſcriptures might haue hope. <hi>Ro.</hi> 15.4. So comfortable, that in the opening they make mens heart to burne within them. <hi>Luc:</hi> 24.32. and filles them with ioy. <hi>Theſe things haus I ſpoken vnto you, that your ioy might be full: Iob:</hi> 15.11. Therefore cryes <hi>S. Auſtine, Domine Ieſu, ſint caſtae delitiae mea ſcripturae tuae:</hi> and <hi>Dauid Eloquia, &amp;c. Thy word is ſweet vnto my mouth, yea ſweeter then the hony and hony combe:</hi> And if it be of this nature, read what is it when the bread is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and diuided, then we haue the pure marrow, the <hi>Manna,</hi> and meaning of it. So that at euery ſermon we haue <hi>lautas epulas,</hi> plenty and change of diſhes.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard the meate at this feaſt. Nor muſt you thinke that drinke is wanting, for they haue (which I named before,) water of Teares, which let none deſpiſe; For vpon ſuch eyes as ſtand brim-full of repentant teares, Chriſt works a miracle, &amp; turnes their ſorrow into the wine of gladnes and heauenly conſolation. They haue ſecondly <hi>Dauids</hi> cuppe of <hi>Gods ſaluation,</hi> which ouerflowes: For as the violl of his wrath runnes out for fierceneſſe, ſo the cup of his ſaluation runnes ouer for fulnes. Againe, they haue the loue of Chriſt, which the Spouſe ſaith, is better then wine. <hi>Cant:</hi> 1.1. And laſt of all, <hi>Dauid</hi> tells vs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14977:15"/>that God will make ſuch to drinke out of the riuer of his pleaſures. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 36.8. If you demand what ſauce the children of God haue at this feaſt of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? I muſt anſwere, croſſes and afflictions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; tribulations, which (as Phyſitians roule pills in ſugar, and make that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ehiculum medicinae,</hi>) God ſo wiſely mixes, and tempers with their wholſom food, that they are not able to diſtinguiſh twixt meat and ſauce, but nouriſh their growth in grace, as wel with the one as with the other. So that they finde no tart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, no ſharpnes, no bitternes in theſe afflictions, no, not in death it ſelfe, for as God ſweetly diſpoſes and pleaſantly compounds the reſt: ſo <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is theyr taſter in this. He hath taſted death for all. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.9. This is their maine cheare: To this, <hi>Sage,</hi> and <hi>Succo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Marioram</hi> gentle, <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> &amp; <hi>Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,</hi> and <hi>Hearb-grace,</hi> are ſprinckled in for ſalades. And all this before the banquet. For that comes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein as wee ſee at feaſts, the ſame things ſerue for the Banquet too, but otherwiſe cooked, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed: ſo it may happily fall out in this, for remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, and hope of euerlaſting glory, are (ſaies <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer,</hi> the ſweet-meats to the feaſt of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; And as for fruits, as we are called in ſcripture, the firſt fruits of his creatures: ſo (if we be of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> companie) we haue the firſt fruits of his ſpirit, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.23. where of S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſerues in often a brace: <hi>Grace &amp; peace in God the Father, &amp;c.</hi> And oftentimes a leaſe, <hi>Grace, mercie, and truth, &amp;c.</hi> And wee finde almoſt a douzen in a diſh, <hi>Galath.</hi> 5.22.23. The fruits of the ſpirit, is <hi>loue, ioy peace, long-ſuffering, gentlenes, goodnes, Faith, meekenes, temperance, &amp;c.</hi> After theſe come in all choyce and rare dainties, mentioned in <hi>Iſay:</hi> 11.2. <hi>Wiſedome, and vnderſtanding, councell, and ſtrength, Knowledge, and the feare of the Lord,</hi> which are called in <hi>Eſay,</hi> 55. by the names of <hi>Water milke, and wine, ſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, Fatnes, &amp;c.</hi> In other places, they are iointly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14977:16"/>named the <hi>Annoynting, the oyle of gladnes,</hi> where with as <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> was annoynted aboue his fellowes, ſo being (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtiles him) <hi>the Byſhop of our ſoules:</hi> he doth therewith annoint and conſecrate vs, Prieſts vnto God, euen an holy, and a Royall Prieſthood. 1.2.9. which is an oynement, moſt ſauory and redolent, <hi>The ſauour of thine oyntment is better then all ſpices: Cant.</hi> 4.10, which heauenly Oyle is ſhead in our hearts, by the holy Ghoſt that is giuen vs. <hi>Rom</hi> 5.5. Ther's an other banquetting diſh of loue and knowledge mine together, For knowledge of it ſelfe is too windy; it ſwell a man like puff paſt, and ſhewe him vp, but loue modefies and allayes it, and makes it wholeſome.</p>
            <p>Then comes in the louing kindneſſe of the Lorde, making the Good-mans eſtate equall with that of Kings, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tolde <hi>Agrippa,</hi> in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde God is ſayde to crowne vs with louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; tender mercy, Pſa. 103.4. So that righteous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſo many crowned Kings. Nay, faieth the Apoſtle, more then conquerours, Rom. 8. Whats more then conquerours? Why, Triumphers: for hee makes vs to triumph in Chriſt, 2. Cor. 2.14. Next the good &amp; faithfull ſoule receiues in this banquet, a Chriſtall bellie, made of the blood of Chriſt; not <hi>Sanguis Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conis,</hi> but <hi>Leonis,</hi> of the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> or rather; of the Lambe of God, a ſtrange and ſtrong reſtoratiue, more then all their pectorall rowles, or Mythridate, or <hi>aurum potabile;</hi> that will fetch life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſooner then all their cordiall waters: for this indeede is the true <hi>Aqua Coeleſtis,</hi> and <hi>Roſa Solis,</hi> of the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, one droppe whereof, is ſufficient for a thouſand worlds. After this comes that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that full aſſurance of faith in Chriſt, which is the true <hi>Manus Chriſti:</hi> that paſſeth all their Marmelade, Succate. And laſt of all is that food of Angels: hidden Manna, ſo called, <hi>Apos.</hi> 2.17. which is a kind of ſecret conſolation, which the Lord infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14977:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>into the hearts of his faiththfull ſeruantes: ſuch as keepe a good conſcience, which farres exceeds all the ſtellifyed meates of Alchymiſts and Coniurers, tranſports and rauiſheth the ſoule of man, as S. Peter hauing a taſte of it, talkes of building Tabernacles, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> it ſeemes, had ſome reliſh of it, where hee ſayeth, I ouerflow exceedingly, I abound with all ioy, amidſt our tribulation: This it makes a man forget all ſenſuall pleaſure, and is not only food, but a riuer of ſpirituall drinke to the ſoule, which prouokes <hi>Auſtin</hi> to cry; <hi>Pota me Domine torrente vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lupt atis, vt nil iam mundanorum libeat deguſtare veneualae dulcedimis.</hi> Giue mee of this drinke, Lord, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not the poyſonous delights of the world. This occaſioned the ſame Father to entitle a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, a paradiſe abounding with graces and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights: And <hi>Hugo,</hi> to ſtile it a garden of delight, and the golden diuing Chamber of the holy Ghoſt. And ſo much for the meat and drinke.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that commends a feaſt, is the Company. It is a ſpeech of a Romane in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that hee had only eaten, not ſupped when he wanted company. Now company are eyther gueſts or atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants: both theſe magnifie the feaſts of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: for the gueſts are the bleſſed &amp; glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: For a good conſcience (wee haue heard) hath the ſpirit his boſom-friend; ſuch a foule the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the cloſet of the holy-Ghoſt, &amp; for his father, our Sauiour tells vs, <hi>Iohn:</hi> 14. to the man that loues him, his Father will come, and dwell with him: And of himſelfe. <hi>Rerel:</hi> 3.20. Beholde, <hi>I ſtand at the dore, and knocke, if any man heare my voyce and open the dore, I will come in to him, and will ſuppe with him, and he with me.</hi> Our beſt friends vſe to be beſt welcome; and can a man haue a dearer Gueſt, a better friend then Chriſt Ieſus: for he vouchſafes to call good men his friends, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 15.13. his kinſmen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in other places his brethren,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14977:17"/>his children, his mother, his Spowſe, to ſhew that he loues vs, with all theſe loues: the friendes, the kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans; the brothers, the fathers, the wifes: Nay, his is as high aboue theſe, as is Heauen aboue earth, and therefore hauing him our gueſt, wee haue him in the knot, and ring, and packe of all our frinds together. As for the Attendants at this feaſt, they are no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wayters, ordinary Seruing men: but the bleſſed Angells of heauen. Are they not all miniſtring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſent out to miniſter for their ſakes, that ſhall be heyres of ſaluation? <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. <hi>vlt:</hi> who as they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to Chriſt, aſſoone as the diuell forſooke him, ſo when we are once ridde of the diuell of hell, of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience, they preſently be our ſeruants; and as they miniſtred to him in his hunger: for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells to all his in thyrſt and hunger, are (as <hi>Luther</hi> is bolde to ſay) Cookes and Butlers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third circumſtance of a feaſt, is light, t'is therefore a plague (ſaith <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi>) to a couetous wretch, that alwayes he eates in darknes: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what is a feaſt without light? ſo tis in the ſoule: therefore the wicked hart or conſcience is deſcribed in ſcripture to be voyde of light, full of darknes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theyr cogitations darkned: <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 4.18. Their fooliſh heart is full of darknes. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.21. And all they can doe, all their works are deedes of darknes. <hi>Rom:</hi> 13.12. But the children of God, like the land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> haue light enough: they walke in the light, and are children of the day, tranſlated from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darknes into his meruellous light. So as the righteous ſoule needes no taper or torch-light at his feaſt, ſpecially if we reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what company is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Firſt, there is the comforter, the bright and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpirit, which makes him that is ſpirituall to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne all things, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. There is alſo God the Father in companie, who is <hi>Pater luminum:</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Light. <hi>Iames,</hi> 1.17. and Chriſt Ieſus, who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14977:17"/>is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Light of the world, the day-spring from on high,</hi> a Light to bee reuealed to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the glorie of his people <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 As for the laſt circumſtance of Muſicke, the good conſcience hath inough; euery ſtring of his heart ſounds out a pleaſant melody, pleaſing in the cares of Almighty God himſelfe. Firſt, God playes on the heart ſtrings of his children, <hi>Vt ſila cordaram, ſic cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da filioram tangit,</hi> and moues them eaſily, then they ſound forth his prayſe in Pſalmes and hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs, making melody in their hearts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: at which Muſicke, the enuious diuell fta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds without the dore, like the elder brother in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fretting and diſcontent at the noyſe hee heares within: Secondly, the very afflictions here endured, as they are muſicke to a good conſcience, according to that of <hi>Prudencius; Tormenta, carcer, vngulae ſtriden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que flammis, &amp;c.</hi> All kind of tortures are pleaſant to a Chriſtian. Thy rodde (ſayeth <hi>Dauid</hi>) comforts mee. So likewiſe do they ſerue as ſo many muſicall iuſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prayſe God withall: as it was ſayd of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> the Martyr; <hi>Tot ecce laudant ora, quet ſunt vui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera,</hi> That all his gaping woundes were ſo many mouthes to celebrate Gods glory. And as their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, ſo their prayers &amp; teares are ſweeter muſicke in the eares of God, then Spheares, or the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Angels. Eſpecially, the repentant teares of a ſad ſoule, are an excellent Muſicke in voyces, that is heard as hie as heauen; So God tels <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> Thou haſt wept before me, and I haue heard it; &amp; it ſeemes the Angels heare it too: for it is ſayde of them, that they reioyce at a weeping ſinners conuerſion. And yet here is not all: For it is not onely a feaſt, but a continuall feaſt. The royall feaſt of <hi>Aſſuerus, in Eſt.</hi> 1. laſted but a 100. &amp; 80. dayes: but this is euerlaſting. A good conſcience then holds out in all weathers, which made <hi>Pindar</hi> call it the ſweet nurſe of a mans
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14977:18"/>old age. The comfort of prophane worldlings, like a torrent ſoone runnes it ſelfe drie and away, but the godly mans peace is like a perpetuall ſpring, hee growes and goes on in grace. Therefore in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> onely the ſtayres of the Temple were left vnnumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vnmeaſured, intimating, that the aſcenſion to God grace, and ſo to his glory is endleſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods mercy &amp; his grace, are ſtiled a rich grace; a great mercy, a ſuperabundant grace, a laſting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, better then all conſerues and preſerues, of which the Poet ſayeth; <hi>Inamareſcunt epulae ſine fine petitae,</hi> They will grow bitter, if common: but this is as ſweet, and tender, and delicate to a man in his age, as in his youth, nay ſweeter and ſweeter, like that wine in <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. beſt at laſt. So that the good mans feaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes at All-Saints, at our ſanctity and holines here; and laſts till the great generall Purification, till our bodies be deputed of all earthly droſſe, &amp; our foules of ſinne, that is, till wee arriue at Heauen. It is true, the godly mans condition, in reſpect of death is all one with the wicked; hee muſt die: but when death, like a Voyder, comes to take away, hee doth not then riſe from his banquet diſcontent, as the wicked ſoule; <hi>Vitaque cum gemita fugie indignata ſub vmbras:</hi> with noyſe and murmuring, but he departs, <hi>Cedit vticonuiua ſatur,</hi> like a full gueſt ſatiſſied, to ſleepe, to reſt, till ſupper. For ſo death, to a man that hath this feaſt of a good conſcience, is but a Feaſt of ſlumber till ſupper time, till hee come to that Marriage Supper of the Lambe, ſpoken of in <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.9. Where for plenty and variety of meate and drinke, he ſhalbe better then before: for it is ſaide, in Gods preſence is fulnes of ioy, and at his right hand are pleaſures for euermore. <hi>pſalm:</hi> 16.11. where for his Banquet of grace, he ſhall haue one of glorie; for the fruits of the ſpirit heere, he ſhall there feed on the fruits of the Tree of life, which beares 12. manner of fruits, <hi>Reuel:</hi> 22.2. And for Light he ſhall need none
<pb facs="tcp:14977:18"/>there: neither Sunne, nor Moone to lighten that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie. <hi>For the glory of God doth lighten it, &amp; the Lambe is the light of it.</hi> And for company, beſide man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that ſhal come from the Eaſt &amp; from the weſt, and ſhall ſit down at table, with <hi>Abrah: Iſack &amp; Iacob,</hi> in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11. &amp; a huge nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in <hi>Reu:</hi> 7 9. which no man can nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, of all nations &amp; kindreds, which ſhal ſtand before the <hi>Lamb,</hi> clothed with long white robes, &amp; palmes in their hands, and beſides the fellowſhip of Saints and Angels, the ſoule ſhall there enioy her olde company of the <hi>Glorious &amp; bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> and then ſhall ſee <hi>GOD;</hi> not any longer in <hi>aenig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matè,</hi> but ſee him face to face, &amp; know euen as ſhee is knowne. As alſo ſhe ſhall ſtill retaine her ancient at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of the bleſſed Angells, &amp; <hi>our bleſſed Sauiour</hi> telleth vs, he wil wayt vpon vs. In the <hi>Saturnals</hi> (ſaith <hi>Macrobius</hi>) maſters ſerue their ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; at this high <hi>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet, our Lord &amp; M. Cor. Ieſ. wil gyrd himſelf, &amp; be our ſeruitour.</hi> And laſtly, for <hi>Muſicke.</hi> All the Angels ſhall loudly ſound their Clarions. The Prophets ſhal bring their harpes of gold and Iuory. And the glorious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Martyrs ſhall bring their trumpets of ſiluer, &amp; all the whole Quire &amp; <hi>Chorus</hi> of heauen, ſhall ſing <hi>Huleluiah,</hi> that ſong of 3. parts, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Saboath, Amen, bleſſing &amp; glory, &amp; wiſdome, and thanksgiuing, and honor, &amp; power be vnto our God for euer and ouer, Amen.</hi> In a word, to reſolue this ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into vſe &amp; practiſe: Let vs learne, not to loue the world, or the vaine profit &amp; fooliſh pleaſures of this life: we ſee there is no true mirth, no ſound ioy to be found in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: let therfore vain worldlings pamper, &amp; fill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with ſuch painted food, and ſo obtaine perhaps a painted tombe, or a partial flouriſhing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph after death: But let vs labour for the meate that periſheth not, the food that laſteth euer, as gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, abundance of content: namely, <hi>a good conſcience,</hi> which is both a feaſt in this life, and a preparatiue to a banquet in the life to come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Gloria Deo in Excelſis.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
